Register of the Lou Henry Hoover Miscellaneous Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Lou Henry Hoover miscellaneous papers
1820-1984
XX656
Hoover Institution Archives
1 manuscript box, 7 oversize boxes, 1 envelope, memorabilia (10 linear feet)
Passport, 1913; war zone passes, 1918; sketch of Lou Henry Hoover, 1931; portfolio of reproductions of drawings of Spanish missions in California, 1933; and sketches of the White House, Capitol Building, Washington Monument, and Mount Vernon.
Hoover, Lou Henry, 1874-1944.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1874 Born, Iowa
1894 Enters Stanford University, where she meets her future husband, Herbert Hoover, also a Stanford student in the Geology Department
1899 Marries Herbert Hoover
1900-1918 Travels extensively with her husband in his career as an engineer, living in China, Siberia, and London, among other places. Accompanies Herbert Hoover on some trips associated with relief activities during and after World War I, and is active herself in charitable work
1919 Supervises construction of home on Stanford campus
1921-1929 Lives in Washington, D.C., where her husband is Secretary of Commerce. Is active in the Girl Scout movement
1929-1933 First Lady of the United States
1944 Dies
Scope and Content Note
The Lou Henry Hoover collection in the Hoover Institution Archives preserves selected items associated with the life of First Lady Lou Henry Hoover, the wife of Herbert Hoover, 31st president of the United States.
Lou Henry Hoover met her future husband when they were both students at Stanford University, and the collection contains artifacts relating to her time at Stanford, including her senior yearbook. The Hoovers would later return to the Stanford campus, building a home there, and there are photographs and art work in the collection depicting the Lou Henry Hoover House, as the Hoover residence would later be named.
Herbert Hoover's career as a mining engineer took him to many different countries, and he and Lou Henry Hoover lived abroad for more than a decade prior to World War I. The collection contains a set of souvenir spoons purchased by Lou Henry Hoover on her foreign travels.
It was while living in London in 1914, at the outbreak of hostilities, that Lou Henry Hoover and her husband became involved in helping Americans leave war-torn Europe. Herbert Hoover went on to head the Commission for Relief in Belgium from 1915-1919, and his wife assisted him in this activity. There are examples of needlepoint lace in the collection that were given to the Hoovers in recognition of their efforts on behalf of Belgium.
The Hoovers spent the 1920s in Washington, D.C., where Herbert Hoover served first as Secretary of Commerce and then as President. Lou Henry Hoover took a keen interest in the architecture of the nation's capital, and there is a significant collection of historical prints of Washington scenes, especially of the White House, in the collection.
The remainder of the collection is comprised mainly of honorary degrees and other awards received by Lou Henry Hoover in the course of a career in public service. Many other items associated with Lou Henry Hoover are on permanent display in the exhibit cases of the Hoover Library, located in Hoover Tower on the campus of Stanford University. Additional materials pertaining to her life and to the Lou Henry Hoover House can be found in the collections of the Green Library, Stanford University. The largest collection of archival materials relating to Lou Henry Hoover is located in the Herbert Hoover Presidential Library, West Branch, Iowa.
Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964.; California--Pictorial works.; Drawings.; Spanish missions of California--Pictorial works.; United States.; Washington (D.C.)--Pictorial works.
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1898-1984 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Certificates, diplomas, and proclamations; clipping; invitation; nomination form; year book; and war zone passes, all arranged alphabetically by physical form.
  - Certificates, diplomas, and proclamations.
    General note
    See also OVERSIZE MATERIALS
    - Embossed cover of Lou Henry Hoover's Stanford diploma, undated (Folder 1: 1)
    - Certificate given to Lou Henry Hoover on the occasion of her being awarded the Médaille de la Reine Elisabeth, Belgium, 1919 June 19 (Folder 1: 2)
    - Proclamation given to Lou Henry Hoover upon her being awarded the Croix de Chevalier de l'Ordre de Léopold, Belgium,., 1919 September (Folder 1: 3)
      Includes letter regarding this award, 1919
    - Diploma issued upon award of honorary doctorate, Whittier College, Whittier, California, 1928 August 17 (Folder 1: 4)
    - Diploma given in award of honorary doctorate, Goucher College, Baltimore, Maryland, 1931 April 24 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Clipping, 1928 July 22 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Invitation for Stanford commencement exercises, 1898 (Folder 1: 7)
  - Nomination form,., 1984 (Folder 1: 8)
    Photocopy of form submitted by James P. Delgado in nomination of the Lou Henry Hoover House for inclusion in the National Register of Historic Places. Includes a floor plan of the house
  - Year Book. Printed copy of Stanford Quad, 1898 (Folder 1: 9)
  - War zone passes, 1918 (Folder 1: 10)
    Documents issued to Lou Henry Hoover by the U.S. government for entry into port areas in New York and New Jersey
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1915-1934 (Box 1)
  Letters, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
  - Russell, Mary, 1915 (Folder 1: 11)
  - Rutt, Anna H., 1933-1934 (Folder 1: 12)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS, 1820-1963 (Box 2-7)
  Art works, ceremonial award case, clothing and handicrafts, diplomas, passport, photographs, printed matter, and silverware, arranged alphabetically by physical form.
  - Art works.
    See also MISCELLANY, below
    - "The Ascent to the Capitol, Washington," engraving by Bartlett, London, undated (Folder 2: 1)
    - "Capitol - Washington," tinted engraving published by Hermann J. Meyer, undated (Folder 2: 2)
    - "Capitol of the U.S., Washington," engraving by W. Goodacre, undated (Folder 2: 3)
    - Lithograph by C. Allen Sherman depicting the Washington Monument, undated (Folder 2: 4)
    - "President's House," tinted print depicting lithograph by August Köllnac(?), undated (Folder 2: 5)
    - "The President's House (1799)," reproduction of sketch, undated (Folder 2: 6)
    - "President's House, North Front," lithograph, undated (Folder 2: 7)
    - "The President's House, Washington," engraving, undated (Folder 2: 8)
    - "Presidentens i de Fórente Staterna Residence i Washington," lithograph by C. Müller, undated (Folder 2: 9)
    - "St. John's Church in the City of Washington, with the President's House as It Appeared in 1816, When the Church Was Built," copy of a water color by Benjamin Latrobe, undated (Folder 2: 10)
    - "A Front View of the President's House, Washington," engraving, 1820 April (Folder 2: 11)
    - "East Front of the Capitol," engraving of a drawing by C. Bullfinch, 1821 (Folder 2: 12)
    - "West Front of the Capitol," engraving of a drawing by C. Bullfinch, 1821 (Folder 2: 13)
    - "A Back View of the Capitol, Washington," engraving, 1827 (Folder 2: 14)
    - "United States Capitol," engraving of a drawing by C. Bullfinch,", 1827 (Folder 2: 15)
    - "The President's House, Washington," print from copper plate, 1830 (Folder 2: 16)
    - "The Capitol, Washington, D.C.," lithograph by T. Doughty, 1832 (Folder 2: 17)
    - "The President's House, Washington," lithograph of a sketch by A. A. Hoftag, 1834 (Folder 2: 18)
    - "The Capitol," engraving, 1840 (Folder 2: 19)
    - "The Capitol," engraving, 1845 (Folder 2: 20)
    - "Das Capitol von Washington," engraving by Kraus, 1850 (Folder 2: 21)
    - "The New Capitol (Washington)," tinted engraving published by Hermann J. Meyer, 1851 (Folder 2: 22)
    - "View of Washington City," lithograph, 1860 (Folder 2: 23)
    - "The White House, Washington, D.C.," print,., ca. 1930 (Folder 2: 24)
      Signed by Herbert and Lou Henry Hoover
    - Three lithographs by J. C. Claghorn,., ca. 1931 (Folder 2: 25)
      One depicting the Washington monument; one, Mt. Vernon; and one, the White House
    - "From the South Portico of the White House," lithograph by J. C. Claghorn,., 1931 (Folder 2: 26)
      Three prints, of which two are signed by Herbert and Lou Henry Hoover
    - Pencil sketch of Lou Henry Hoover, 1931 (Folder 2: 27)
    - Painting depicting the Lou Henry Hoover Memorial YMCA, Palo Alto, California, 1960 (Folder 2: 28)
  - Ceremonial award case for the Croix de Chevalier de l'Ordre de Léopold, 1919 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Clothing and handicrafts
    - Beaded gown worn by Lou Henry Hoover (Folder 3: 2)
    - String of beads worn by Lou Henry Hoover (Folder 3: 3)
    - Eight pieces of Belgian needlepoint lace presented to Lou Henry Hoover, undated (Box 4-5)
      Contains lace tablecloths and shawls given to the Hoovers in appreciation of the support the Commission for Relief in Belgium gave to the lace workers during World War I and lace items made during and/or shortly after World War I to commemorate the aid given to the Belgium lace makers by the Commission for Relief in Belgium (C.R.B). Also includes ornate presentation cover for lace.
      Citations on lace descriptions from: Kellogg, Charlotte, Bobbins of Belgium, Funk & Wagnalls Co., New York. 1920; Merritt, Elaine. “War Lace: Commemorating Victory and Determination,” Piecework Magazine, July/August, 1999, pg. 24-29' Wardle, Patricia. “War and Peace: lace designs by the Belgian sculptor Isidore de Rudder,” Bulletin van het Rijksmuseum, Jaarg. 37, Nr. 2. 1989. pg. 73-90.
      - Black triangular shawl of handmade Chantilly bobbin lace (Box 4)
        Approximately 9’ x 5’. The central motif is of an arched garden arbor (or trellis) surrounded by large tropical leaves and flowers. [See Kellogg, page 127, for discussion of Chantilly lace production during the war.]
      - Cream colored triangular shawl of handmade bobbin lace motifs appliqued to a machine-made netting (Box 4)
        Approximately 9’ x 4.5’. Floral motifs with scroll designs throughout. The centers of the flowers and the scrolls contain needle lace fillings.
      - A small item of mixed Brussels Duchess lace (Box 4)
        Measured at 11” x 7”, in which the bobbin-made lace with floral motifs has been applied to a machine-made ground and embellished with needle lace dots and rings. Perhaps it was intended to decorate the end of a scarf or some other article of clothing.
      - A piece of heavy, woven fabric (Box 4)
        Approximately 48” x 14”, with a printed pattern, woven with beige and light tan colored threads of varying thicknesses and overprinted (perhaps block printed) with a slightly darker shade of tan. It seems to be a remnant, perhaps of a length of upholstery fabric and perhaps done by a noted Belgian artist. [Several Belgium artists created designs for the Lace Committee of the C. R. B. See discussion of the work of one of these artist, M. de Rudder, in Kellogg, pg. 195 and in article by Wardle]
      - Round doily in filet lace (Box 5)
        Approximately 10” with the Seal of the United States of America darned into the handmade netting.
      - Fan-leaf of Point de Gaze needle lace, designed by artist Lucie Rothschild-Lambert for the Lace Committee of the C. R. B. (Box 5)
        The center of the fan-leaf depicts eight human figures, with the lead figure holding the crown of victory and an olive branch as the figures soar over the burning cities of Belgium. Many of the “animals of the allies” are worked into the swirling design on each side of the fan-leaf, below the figures. To the right are the Belgian lion, the Portuguese wyvern, the Great Britain unicorn, the Russian bear, and a small dove holding an olive branch in its beak. On the left can be found the Portuguese wyvern again, the Italian lion, the American eagle, the French rooster, and a lamb. Below these can be found narrow borders with implements of war depicted: rifles, swords, packs, and what are perhaps grenades and gas masks. Below these, on the left, is worked the name of the artist who designed the lace, Rothschild-Lambert, the year 1914 and the initials C.R.B. The entire fan-leaf is edged in a narrow needle lace border.
      - Square tablecloth inset with needle lace emblems for the United States and Belgium (Box 5)
        Approximately 46” x 46”. There are also twelve needle lace stars and embroidered wheat sheaves that contain cutwork. The American eagle lace insets are in the center of the cloth as well as the four corners. Inset along the four sides of the cloth is the Belgium lion motif, also done in needle lace with the date of 1915/6 and Belgique worked in the lace. There is a 4” wide, floral border of Point de Paris bobbin lace on the outer edge of the cloth. [See Kellogg, plate fp, 89 for an example of smaller cloth with the same American eagle inset and the same embroidered wheat sheaves.]
      - Round tablecloth with bobbin lace inserts representing the emblems of the allied nations (Box 5)
        Approximately 40.5” in diameter. The bobbin lace inserts that depict the emblems of the allies include: the Japanese chrysanthemum at the center of the cloth, surrounded by the two narrow bobbin lace inserts with the date of 1914-1915, beyond that are the bobbin lace insets depicting the coats of arms for France, Great Britain, Imperial Russia, Italy, Rumania, Montenegro, Portugal, Belgium and Serbia. Throughout the cloth there are elongated stars and triangles done with hemstitching. The outside border is a wide border of Point de Paris bobbin lace showing “the animals of the allies:” the Russian bear, Belgian lion, French cock, and the British unicorn. [See Kellogg, plate fp 161 for an example of this same border.]
      - Square tablecloth with eight squares of Point de Venise needle lace depicting emblems of the allies (Box 5)
        Approximately 50” x 50.” These needle lace squares are set into the cloth with alternating squares of Flemish mixed lace (bobbin lace motifs set into needle lace grounds), and squares of cutwork with embroidery. The allied nations represented in the needle lace squares are (from the top of the cloth and right to left) Serbia, France, Great Britain, Montenegro, Belgium, Italy, Imperial Russia, and Japan. The outer edge of the cloth is finished with a wide Point de Venise needle lace border.
  - Diplomas issued in award of honorary degrees to Lou Henry Hoover
    - Honorary doctorate, Swarthmore College, 1929 (Folder 6: 1)
    - Honorary doctorate, Elmira College, 1930 June 9 (Folder 6: 2)
    - Honorary doctorate, Wooster College, 1932 May 14 (Folder 6: 3)
    - Honorary master of art degree, Tufts University, 1932 June 15 (Folder 6: 4)
  - Passport,., 1913 (Box-folder 7: 1)
    Diplomatic passport issued in London to Lou Henry Hoover for her trip to Russia, 1913 October 10
  - Photographs, 1928-1955
    - One print depicting the exterior of the White House, undated (Folder 7: 2)
    - One print depicting Lou Henry Hoover, undated (Folder 7: 3)
    - Six prints depicting the exterior and interior of the Lou Henry Hoover House, undated (Folder 7: 4)
    - One print depicting the White House, undated (Folder 7: 5)
    - One print depicting Lou Henry Hoover, 1928 (Folder 7: 6)
    - One print depicting the exterior of Lou Henry Hoover School, Whittier, California, 1955 (Folder 7: 7)
  - Printed matter, 1933-1963
    - The Romance of El Camino Real,., 1933 (Folder 7: 8)
      Book of illustrations of California missions, encased in a leather book cover embossed with the title and Lou Henry Hoover's name. Includes presentation certificate
    - Journal of the American Institute of Architects,., 1963 January (Folder 7: 9)
      Printed copy of serial issue containing illustrations of Washington, D.C.
  - Silverware. Twelve souvenir spoons collected by Lou Henry Hoover during her travels abroad,., 1900-1910 (Folder 7: 10)
    Includes invitation, note, and postcard, all relating to Jessie S. Jones, aunt of Lou Henry Hoover, establishing the provenance of the spoons
- MISCELLANY, 1792 (Art racks and map case)
  Three framed prints and one presentation folder for Belgian lace
  - One framed Chinese print on fabric, undated (Art-racks Art racks)
  - One framed print, "Plan of the City of Washington,", 1792
  - One framed photograph depicting Lou Henry Hoover, undated
  - One ornate presentation folder for Belgian lace, undated (Map-case Map case)
- INCREMENTAL MATERIALS (Box 8)
  This addition to the collection has not yet been described. Please let the Hoover Institution Archives know if you would like to see this material described.